<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Theory | Dominik Lentrodt</title>
    <link>https://dlentrodt.github.io/tag/theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dlentrodt.github.io/tag/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Theory</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dlentrodt.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Theory</title>
      <link>https://dlentrodt.github.io/tag/theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear quantum optics</title>
      <link>https://dlentrodt.github.io/project/xraycavtheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dlentrodt.github.io/project/xraycavtheory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When thinking of nuclei and quantum optics, the first topics that come to mind are nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and diamond vacancy centers. However, there is more!
Many nuclei feature ultra-narrow transitions in the hard X-ray domain, which can be excited by radioactive sources or modern X-ray facilities, such as X-ray free electron lasers (XFELs).
These systems provide a promising candidate for the new field of X-ray quantum optics 
&lt;a href=&#34;#external-references&#34;&gt;[1-2]&lt;/a&gt;. Compared to the alternative electronic resonances at these energies, nuclei provide excellent coherence properties, promising access to truly quantum phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, Mössbauer nuclei feature incredibly low decoherence, with quality factors of 10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt; up to 10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;, often outcompeting even the best superconducting qubits in this regard, which are nowadays being used to build quantum computers. While this simple feature hints at what an exciting platform these nuclei provide, it is clear that we are not going to build a nuclear quantum computer any time soon. One main reason is that operating these extreme quantum systems is challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of my PhD research is to find out how far modern X-ray sources can take Mössbauer nuclei in the quantum direction. The big questions include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we drive the transitions efficiently?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which quantum dynamical processes can be induced?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we achieve non-linear effects?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to detect quantum effects and correlations of the X-ray light?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to obtain nuclear observables?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One exciting platform to investigate these questions is nuclear cavity QED, where the interaction between X-rays and nuclei is enhanced by a thin-film material stack (see figure), which in effect behaves much like a Fabry-Perot cavity in the optical regime. One can achieve collective effects in this setup, which have already been investigated extensively in the semi-classical sector at low excitations 
&lt;a href=&#34;#external-references&#34;&gt;[3-9]&lt;/a&gt;. The idea here is that in addition to the astonishing development in X-ray source technology of the last decades, we will also require control techniques (see also the &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.mpi-hd.mpg.de/personalhomes/lentrodt/project/coherentcontrol/&#39;&gt;related project&lt;/a&gt; on coherent control) and tailored systems to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of answering the questions above is to see if we can achieve quantum effects, which would provide a completely new platform for quantum dynamics with extreme transitions. At the same time, quantum effects could be used to improve the many existing applications of these systems, ranging from materials science to metrology. I develop theoretical methods to answer these questions, and also contribute to and perform experiments at large scale X-ray facilities to investigate the effects that we find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;external-references&#34;&gt;External references&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/09500340.2012.752113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[1] B. W. Adams et al. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Modern Optics&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;60&lt;/strong&gt;, 2-21 (2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.09317&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[2] B. W. Adams et al. &lt;em&gt;arXiv:1903.09317&lt;/em&gt; (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1187770&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[3] R. Röhlsberger et al. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;328&lt;/strong&gt;, 1248 (2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10741&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[4] R. Röhlsberger et al. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;482&lt;/strong&gt;, 199–203 (2012)&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.111.073601&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[5] K. P. Heeg et al. &lt;em&gt;Phys. Rev. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;111&lt;/strong&gt;, 073601 (2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.207401&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[6] K. P. Heeg et al. &lt;em&gt;Phys. Rev. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;114&lt;/strong&gt;, 207401 (2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.203601&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[7] K. P. Heeg et al. &lt;em&gt;Phys. Rev. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;114&lt;/strong&gt;, 203601 (2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nphoton.2016.77&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[8] J. Haber et al. &lt;em&gt;Nat. Photon.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;, 445–449 (2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41566-017-0013-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[9] J. Haber et al. &lt;em&gt;Nat. Photon.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;, 720–725 (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-publications&#34;&gt;Related publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlentrodt.github.io/publication/heeg2017_science/&#34;&gt;K. P. Heeg et al. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;357&lt;/strong&gt;, 375 (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlentrodt.github.io/publication/lentrodt2020b_prresearch/&#34;&gt;D. Lentrodt et al. &lt;em&gt;arXiv:2003.13859&lt;/em&gt; (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open quantum systems theory</title>
      <link>https://dlentrodt.github.io/project/fewmodetheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dlentrodt.github.io/project/fewmodetheory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As most quantum optical systems, nuclear transitions and X-ray cavities are open by coupling to the environment. Interestingly, due to the extreme properties of the nuclei and the high photon energies, we are facing a number of theoretical challenges and open questions. As a result, I have been developing methods to describe the coupled quantum dynamics of X-rays and nuclei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, the methodology in nuclear resonant scattering has largely been based on semi-classical scattering theory. We are now extending these techniques to describe the full quantum dynamics by interfacing with quantum optical methods. Surprisingly, many of the theoretical questions are currently also being investigated in different fields in the optical domain. In this context, I have also been contributing to platform-independent theory development, using the slightly unusual X-ray perspective and insights from scattering theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, we found that the established input-output formalism from cavity QED has its limitations for highly leaky and overlapping mode resonators, which we often encounter in the hard X-ray domain. Indeed, due to the high precision of the nuclear transitions, effects were observed experimentally 
&lt;a href=&#34;#external-references&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; whose explanation required significant heuristic extensions to standard input-output theory 
&lt;a href=&#34;#external-references&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Motivated by this observation, we developed an ab initio theory deriving the Hamiltonian that input-output theory is based on from first principles 
&lt;a href=&#34;#related-publications&#34;&gt;[a]&lt;/a&gt; and proving an equivalence to wave scattering theory. The result partially resolves a 30-year old question in theoretical quantum optics and provides an interesting approach to simplify continuum baths in general open quantum systems. In a recent paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;#related-publications&#34;&gt;[b]&lt;/a&gt;, we applied the method to &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.mpi-hd.mpg.de/personalhomes/lentrodt/project/xraycavtheory&#39;&gt;nuclear cavity QED&lt;/a&gt;, explaining the origin of previous discrepancies and discovering associated effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current work is focussed on exploring new regimes of nuclear quantum dynamics using these methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- My current work is focussed on solving the resulting quantum dynamics in the low and highly excited sectors. We are employing various techniques that are known from visible quantum optics, including cumulant expansions [[1-2]](#external-references), permutation symmetry [[3]](#external-references), few-photon scattering theory [[4-5]](#external-references) and more.

External references
-------------------
[[1] P. Kirton and J. Keeling, *Phys. Rev. Lett.* **118**, 123602 (2017)](https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.118.123602)  
[[2] M. Zens et al. *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 013856 (2019)](https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.100.013856)  
[[3] N. Shammah et al. *Phys. Rev. A* **98**, 063815 (2018)](https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.98.063815)  
[[4] S. Mahmoodian et al. *Phys. Rev. Lett.* 121, 143601 (2018)](https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.121.143601)  
[[5] R. Trivedi et al. *Phys. Rev. Lett.* **122**, 243602 (2019)](https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.122.243602) //--&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;external-references&#34;&gt;External references&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10741&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[1] R. Röhlsberger et al. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;482&lt;/strong&gt;, 199–203 (2012)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.91.063803&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[2] K. P. Heeg and J. Evers, &lt;em&gt;Phys. Rev. A&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;91&lt;/strong&gt;, 063803 (2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-publications&#34;&gt;Related publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlentrodt.github.io/publication/lentrodt2020a_prx/&#34;&gt;[a] D. Lentrodt and J. Evers, &lt;em&gt;Phys. Rev. X&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;, 011008 (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlentrodt.github.io/publication/lentrodt2020b_prresearch/&#34;&gt;[b] D. Lentrodt et al. &lt;em&gt;arXiv:2003.13859&lt;/em&gt; (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
